Guide to the Lincoln Collection Monuments and Memorials 1850-1927
University of Chicago Library
Lincoln Collection. Monuments and Memorials
1850-1927
10.25 linear feet (6 boxes, 3 oversized folders)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Lincoln Collection, Monuments and Memorials contains photographs and newspaper articles detailing monuments and memorial sites relating to Abraham Lincoln. It also includes printed reproductions of places and events relating to the Civil War. The collection forms part of the William E. Barton Collection of Lincoliana.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Rev. William Eleazar Barton (1861-1930) The Rev. William Eleazar Barton (1861-1930) was one of the early twentieth century's most prominent writers and lecturers on the life of Abraham Lincoln. Born in Sublette, Illinois, in the same year Lincoln assumed the presidency, Barton grew up in an environment heavily influenced by reverence for Lincoln. After pursuing undergraduate studies at Berea College in Kentucky, Barton earned his divinity degree from the Oberlin Theological Seminary in 1890. He served parishes in Tennessee, Ohio, and Massachusetts before becoming the pastor of the First Congregational Church of Oak Park, Illinois, a position he held until his retirement in 1924. Four years later, Barton accepted an appointment as lecturer at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee, where he also organized and served as pastor of the Collegeside Congregational Church.
Barton's work as a writer produced a number of denominational manuals for church organization and a series of books presenting the wisdom and parables of a character he named Safed the Sage. For the last ten years of his life, however, Barton was best known to the public as a prolific author and lecturer on Abraham Lincoln. His publications about Lincoln included The Soul of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Paternity of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Life of Abraham Lincoln (1925), The Great and Good Man (1927), The Women Lincoln Loved (1927), and The Lincoln of the Biographers (1930).
In the course of compiling material for his writings and talks, Barton visited Lincoln sites in Kentucky, Indiana, and Illinois; interviewed surviving Lincoln relatives and acquaintances; and traveled as far as California and England to collect information and conduct genealogical research on the ancestry of the Lincoln family. While acquiring a large collection of books, periodicals, pamphlets, manuscripts, and ephemera related to Lincoln and the Civil War era, Barton also purchased privately or at auction historical materials amassed by other Lincoln collectors such as John E. Burton and Osborn H. Oldroyd.
Scope Note
The Lincoln Collection Monuments and Memorials makes up the portion of the Barton Collection of Lincolniana which maintains photographs and newspaper articles detailing monuments and memorial sites relating to Lincoln. The collection also contains reproductions of places and events relating to the Civil War. The Lincoln Collection Monuments and Memorials is arranged into three series: Series I, Lincoln Monuments and Memorials, Series II, Civil War Places and Events, Series III, Oversize. The images and articles in these series form part of William E. Barton’s extensive collection of Lincolniana.
Series I, Lincoln Monuments and Memorials, consists of photographs, articles, and a map detailing various sites that relate to the life and death of Lincoln. It is divided into three subseries according to location. This series is mainly comprised of sites located in Illinois, but also includes those in Washington D.C., and Kentucky. Sites include Lincoln’s childhood home, the gravesite of his father, Thomas Lincoln, and Ford Theater, where Lincoln was fatally injured. The map is of New Salem, IL where Lincoln resided from 1831-1837. See Series III, Oversize, for additional material.
Series II, Civil War Places and Events, consists of photographs, drawings, and articles on sites and occurrences relating to the Civil War. A large portion of this series contains scrapbook photographs and captions of monuments and memorials located in Gettysburg, PA as well as sites in Virginia and Maryland. These photographs are possible remnants of a trip taken by Barton through select Civil War states during 1900. They have been kept in the order in which they were received. The newspaper clippings as well as the daily illustrated newspapers detail the dedication of various Civil War monuments, including the Soldiers’ National Monument erected in Gettysburg, PA in 1869. The postcards contain photographs of Civil War monuments, a large portion of which are of those in Gettysburg, PA. The illustrations detail various events that occurred throughout the war, including the capture of rebel congressmen, naval conquests, and the execution of prisoners. There are standard and oversize reproductions of various events and places associated with the Civil War, including Lincoln’s signing of the Emancipation Proclamation. There is an oversize map of the United States which was featured in the Illustrated London News in 1861. See Series III, Oversize, for additional material.
Series III, Oversize, contains oversize material and is arranged by size. Included are newspaper clippings, daily illustrated newspapers, maps, and reproductions of various places and events associated with the Civil War.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Barton, William Eleazar; Lincoln, Abraham; Collectors and collecting
INVENTORY
- Series I: Lincoln Monuments and Memorials
  - Subseries 1: District of Columbia
    - Washington, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Washington, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Illinois
    - Bloomington, circa 1918-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Charleston, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chicago, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Danville, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Decatur, circa 1865-1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dixon, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Freeport, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Galesburg, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Goose Nest Prairie, 1895-1913 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Harristown, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Jonesboro, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kaskaskia, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mattoon, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Monticello, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New Salem, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Oregon, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Ottawa, 1905-circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Peoria, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Petersburg, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Pontiac, circa 1919 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Shelbyville, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Springfield, 1858-1923 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Springfield, 1885-1922 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified, circa 1921 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 4: Kentucky
    - Elizabethtown, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fayette County, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Harrodsburg, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Hodgenville, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Jefferson County, circa 1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Knob Creek, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lee County, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Middletown, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Springfield, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Trappist, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 5: New Jersey
    - Harrison, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 6: Pennsylvania
    - Lorane, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Gettysburg, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 7: Virginia
    - Harrisonburg, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Lacey Spring, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - North Farnham Parish, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 8: West Virginia
    - Mineral County, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 9: United Kingdom
    - Great Yarmonth, England, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Hingham, England, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Malmesbury, England, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Swanton-Moreley, England, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 10: Unidentified
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series II: Civil War Places and Events
  - Event, Attack on Forts Jackson and St. Phillips, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Event, Battle and Retreat from Bull Run, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Event, Battle of Chapin’s Farm, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Event, Battle of Malvern Hill, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Event, Battle of Mill Spring, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Event, Battle of Wilson’s Creek, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Event, Bombardment of Port Royal and Fort Sumter, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Event, Burnside’s Fleet, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Event, Capture of Roanoke, Island, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Event, The Charge of Fredericksburg, VA, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Event, Death of Sergeant Dyer, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Event, Destruction of the Gosport Navy Yard, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Event, Destruction of the Privateer Petrel, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Event, Execution of Lincoln Conspirators, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Event, The Fall of Reynolds, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Event, Gen. Kearney’s Charge at the Battle of Chantilly, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Event, Interview, Generals Sherman and Johnston, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Event, Shiloh Battlefield and Battle of Stones Creek, 1862-1863 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Event, Siege of Vicksburg, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Event, Struggle on a Bridge during the Retreat from Manassas, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Event, Surrender of General Lee, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Event, War Bombed Building, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Map of Gettysburg Battlefield and Hospitals, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Place, Chesapeake Hospital, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Place, Dumbarton Avenue Methodist Episcopal Church, circa 1850 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Place, Hampton Roads, VA, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Place, Interior of U.S. Ironclad Monitor “Montauk,” undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Place, Libby Prison, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Place, Liberty Hall, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Place, Prison Camp at Andersonville, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Place, Richmond Theatre, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Place, Soldiers’ and Sailors’ Monument, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Place, Stone Mountain Confederate Memorial, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Place, Vicksburg, MS, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Place, View in the Shenandoah Valley, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Place, View of Antietam Battleground, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, The Bloody Cornfield at Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, The Fond of the Potomac River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 15th Mass Monument at Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, Burnside Bridge at Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook, Durkard Church, Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook, City Hotel, Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook, Hotel Lewis, Hyattstown, MD, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook, Monocacy River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook, Wagon Bridge, Monocacy River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook, Pipers Lane, Antietam Battlefield, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook, Soldiers Monument National Cemetery, Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook, D.R. Miller’s House, Antietam, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, Antietam Battlefield, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook, Road Entering Frederick, MD, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook, Confederate Fort Evans, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook, Methodist Episcopal Church, Leesburg, VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook, Hotel Linden, Leesburg, VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook, “Meade” House, Leesburg, VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook, U.S. National Military Cemetery, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook, Confederate Fort Johnson, Leesburg, VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook, Site of Former Prison (John Brown), Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook, Stone-walled Road, Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Scrapbook, Blackford’s Ford, Potomac River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Scrapbook, Leetown Roller Miller, Leetown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Scrapbook, Ruins of Old Church, Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Scrapbook, Old House, Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Scrapbook, Keyes Ferry, Shenandoah River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Scrapbook, Court House, Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Scrapbook, Watson House, Charlestown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Scrapbook, Home of Major Gen. Charles Lee, Leetown, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Scrapbook, Valley Hotel, Martinsburg, W.VA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Scrapbook, Bluffs, Potomac River, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, “Here General Reynolds Fell,” 1900 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, 17th Pennsylvania Cavalry, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Scrapbook, Howard Avenue, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Scrapbook, Barn of Christian Breckbill, Greenvillage, PA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Scrapbook, Bridge over Yellow Breeches, Boiling Springs, PA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Scrapbook, Soldiers Monument, Carlisle, PA, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Scrapbook, Equestrian Statue of General Meade, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, Crawford’s Arc, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, Site of General Sickles’ Injury, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, Stephens Battery 5th Maine, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, View of Bridge and Monuments, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, Equestrian Statue of Gen. John F. Reynolds, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, 1st New York Light Infantry, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, Devils Den, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, McCurdy School House, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, Emmittsburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, Franklin Hotel, Carlisle, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, 1st Mass Infantry, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, Barlow’s Knoll, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, Monument 44th New York Regiment, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, Confederate Avenue, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, Lee’s Headquarters, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook, High Water Mark, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook, General Meade’s Headquarters, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook, Statue, General Warren, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, General Buford, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook, Monument, 90 Pennsylvania Regiment, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook, Stone House, Gettysburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook, Stone House, Boiling Springs, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook, Miller’s Hotel, Chambersburg, PA, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series III: Oversize
  - The Chattanooga Daily Times, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Diagram of the United States, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Event, 2nd Battle of Bull Run, VA, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Event, Battle, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Event, Battle of Pea Ridge Ark, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Event, Battery “L” 5th U.S. Artillery, Stuart’s Place, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Event, Execution of Four Conspirators, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Event, Grand Review of the Army, Washington, D.C., 1881 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Event, “In Commemoration of the Glorious Victories of 3rd and 9th of April 1865,” Richmond, VA, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Event, Signing of the Proclamation of Emancipation, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Event, “Terrific Engagement Between the ‘Monitor’ 2 guns, ‘Merrimac’ 10 guns, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Map, New Salem, IL, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clipping, circa 1869 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Place, Bird’s Eye View of 6th St. Wharf, Washington, D.C., 1863 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Place, Camp Northumberland, Washington, D.C. 1861 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Place, Camp Wool, Baltimore, MD, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Place, Campbell U.S. General Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Place, Carver Barracks, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Place, Cliffbourne Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1862 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Place, Douglas and Stanton Hospitals, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Place, Finley U.S. General Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Place, Fort Federal Hill, Baltimore, M.D., 1862 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Place, Hartford’s Soldiers Memorial, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Place, Havewood Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Place, Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Place, Lincoln Memorial, Washington, D.C., undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Place, Mount Pleasant Hospitals, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Place, The Republican Wigwam, Chicago, IL, 1860 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Place, Soldier’s Home, Washington, D.C., 1863 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Place, Soldiers Rest, Washington, D.C., 1864 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Place, View of Washington City, D.C., 1862 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Event, Siege of Atlanta, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Map of United States, 1861[located in Lincoln Collection Elephants] (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Place, Bird’s Eye View of Andersonville Prison, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Place, View of Public Square, Atlanta, GA, 1864 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Event, Battle of Gettysburg, undated (Folder Ovrz1)
  - Events and Places, Reviewing the Army at Washington, 23 May, 1865 Gunboats Raising Batteries at Vicksburg, Miss, 16 April, 1863 Crossing the Rapadan [Rapidan], 4 May, 1864 Battle of Lookout Mountain (or the Fight Above the Clouds), 25 November, 1863 Battle of Cold Harbor, 1 June, 1864 Winter Quarters in the Trenches in Front of Petersburg, undated Battle of Shiloh (or Pittsburg Landing), 6-7 April, 1862 Battle of the Wilderness, 5-6 May, 1864 Gen’l Sheridan’s Famous Cavalry Charge at Five Forks, 1 April, 1865 Blowing up the Mine at Petersburg, VA, 30, July 1864 Storming of Fort Donaldson, 16 February, 1862 Battle of Iuka, 20 November, 1862 (Folder Ovrz2)
  - Event, 44th National Encampment, 19-24 September, 1910 (Folder Ovrz3)